today i'm going to teach you guys how to
paint like a pro
but as a homeowner we're going to teach
you all of the skills that you need and
we're going to show you the tools the
rig this is my rig this is it
professional painter this is all you
need
you can pack all the stuff in a knapsack
and take a bus to work
it's not that tricky okay but we're
going to show you techniques and skills
so that you don't get caught in the tape
trap
what i mean by that is there's lots of
videos out there to show homeowners oh
we don't think homeowners have enough
skill to use a paint brush so we're
going to make you put 40 of the tape all
over your room and waste half your day
doing it in this video i'm going to show
you how to avoid that i'm going to show
you how to paint this hallway as fast as
you can tape it
right so no blue tape let's just get
right into the skills and tricks we're
going to teach you everything you need
to know in this video so that you can
master the art of painting because if
you know how to paint you can do things
to your house that are the greatest
return of investment is to paint your
house inside outside kitchen cabinets it
doesn't matter what you want to paint
when you're done this video you're going
to have the skills and confidence to do
it remember on the scale of difficulty
painting is like number one it's the
most easiest thing there is to learn on
the market
but it's the greatest skill to have
because if you can't paint you can't
finish
if you can't finish your project
really shouldn't be starting so let's
learn this skill
let's dive through and watch the whole
video i'm going to show you everything
you need to learn let's just jump right
into the rig okay so here are the
must-haves all right
we've got to have a paint tray
you really want to have a liner
especially as a homeowner
because what the liner does
it allows you to finish your job and
just throw this in the garbage so you
don't have to wash everything
this little yellow arm is
it's it's nice to have but it's not a
definite you're going to want to have a
nice cage like this this is the wooster
cage and yes we're going to have links
for all the tools in the video
description just so you know okay this
is the wooster sherlock handle and this
slides in it has a pin and does positive
lock
never again are you going to have to
paint while the handles are spinning off
this is amazing
once you have that set up you've got the
ability now to extend it
and retract it all right
this
rod reduces your work by about 60 to 70
percent it makes the job effortless
you also need a sleeve
okay we use microfiber
this is a 18 mil
there we go that's my rolling rig you're
also going to want to have a three inch
angle brush
this is my three inch angle brush
doesn't have to cost a fortune you can
get a good one for about 20 bucks
and then i've got my 501 tool all right
this is a scraper and used as a
screwdriver also
when you're all done today
it will clean all the extra paint out of
the roller sleeve okay
by the time you're done painting you're
gonna have almost a quart of paint
sitting in this thing so this
make sure that you don't have to spend
so much time washing your gear it'll
also put the paint back in the can so
you've got it for touch-ups later
all right you're going to want to have
an alpha knife because
have i ever done a job in my entire life
i didn't pull out a knife at least once
of course you're going to want a ladder
if you're vertically challenged like i
am
and you're going to want to pull
some sort of a sanding pad
okay
remember a good paint job is all about
the preparation and if you're not
sanding in between coats you're going to
get a poor performance okay
now in today's video i'm not going to
share
all about patching and touch-ups and all
the repairs we've got videos for that
we'll put a link in the video
description where you can check the link
right here on the cart okay now let's
just jump right into it because the
thing that separates a good paint job
from a bad paint job
is the material it's the paint now i've
been using different paints for a lot of
years been using c2 for the last 12 on
and off in different jobs absolutely
love this paint high wash ability okay
high wear great for high traffic areas
and they have proprietary technology
they use a poly whey as their hardener
okay so the strength in this paint isn't
coming from an oil-based product so
there's no resins which means there's no
shortage no supply issues which is why
we're promoting this right now okay
the other thing it is it has very low
vocs which means when you paint your
house doesn't smell like you painted for
a week
absolutely amazing okay no headaches
cheers to that
when it comes time to paint all you've
really got to do is clean the space put
down a tarp and then you gotta remove
all your cover plates because this is
where the preparation comes in
that's where the knife comes in handy
back out all your screws
take all the cover plates off do not
paint around cover plates
that is not cool
okay all right so the purpose of this
video is not to show you how to paint
from new drywall it's to show you how to
repaint
most people want to do a paint job
because well let's face it the color's
ugly
or they're living in a brand new house
and the builder use really cheap paint
and they can't wash the walls step one
is grab some trim paint and fix all of
these mistakes right here
where they were painting the wall and
they got the wall paint all over the
trim
not cool because if you come along and
you do a nice job you're going to have
three colors sitting right there it's
going to scream so
before you start
take some trim paint
and
make sure that that edge is painted now
i don't care if you get it all over the
wall because you're going to come back
and cut a new line but just make sure
that any old paint is covered up there
we go that's much better same holds true
for the ceilings
you might find that you have to paint
the whole ceiling paint your ceiling if
you have to start with a clean palette
if you need to learn how to paint a
ceiling it's a little different
technique you can click the video link
right here or check the video
description below because in when you're
painting ceilings we follow different
rules and walls okay
it's just about the
which direction you want to paint all
that information's in that video let's
just get on with how to paint your room
next step once you've got your ceiling
lines cleaned up and your trim lines
cleaned up is you're going to want to
sand
just use a sanding sponge if you have to
now you don't have to spend good money
on a rig i'll guarantee you when the
builders painted this
they did not do any sanding
and the walls
feel like sandpaper
now this wall has to be sanded properly
now the coolest thing is we're ready to
paint right now no tape don't waste any
time
it's funny because there are two things
that the painting world never teaches
homeowners
never teaches them to sand which is
amazing because
the difference in a wall that's been
sanded versus a wall that hasn't been
sanded is to the touch you can walk into
any house in the world and just go like
this and if it's not smooth like a
baby's bum
it wasn't sanded and you know because
it's just gritty it feels like a dirty
wall
i think one of the reasons they don't
tell you to sand is because they want
you to not be happy with the finished
product so you buy another gallon of
paint
try doing it all over again i don't know
the other thing they never tell you
is to use a paint stick
come on be honest every time you see a
commercial or a movie any advertisement
from a paint company
they always got somebody standing there
painting the wall like this
oh and everybody thinks that's normal
this is the most abnormal painting
technique in the whole world nobody who
ever made a dollar ninety-five over a
lifetime paints that way there's a
reason for it
hey
this is a lot easier you can extend the
pull and keep your hands below your
heart when you're working which means
half the work
it's not all the stress in your forearms
because you're holding the darn thing
right now you can use two hands
half the work again and on top of that
you can get much even distribution of
the paint
right it's going to blow your mind when
you see how easy this is now just for
the record the color here is bubba
ganoush
it's from
c2 we have a
new arrangement with c2 paint so you
guys can get this great affordable
quality paint okay check the video
description for the details and the deal
that we got for you
this is one of the highest quality
paints on the market today
definitely rivals benjamin moore okay
but we're going to get you a much better
price consider it
they don't use oil based resins
to make their paint hard and washable so
they don't have supply issues
now
i hope this turns out
it looks like i'm going to be painting
cream on cream
no way it's too bad hmm
baba ganoush
yep that's different
all right guys
so the paint brush is brand new right
now okay which i don't have anything
loaded into it
so what i'm doing is i've got about two
and a half inches of paint left in this
can all right
and i'm just pushing the paint into the
brush
and until i get it loaded up enough i'm
not going to try to cut the ceiling line
now the wall here is a flat paint oddly
enough
so what we want to do is we want to
drive our paintbrush nice and slow about
a quarter inch from the ceiling
okay whenever you're painting a new
washable paint over a
something that's flat
you want to
get the first coat of paint on
before you try to be too delicate and
get too close to the surface okay
because the paint doesn't slide it
doesn't move well on on a flat paint so
at the second coat that's when we'll
push that right into the corner you'll
see when we get there this works really
well
while you're on a ladder do the other
side of the hole while you're at it
there we go
all right well today we've got a brand
new person that we've selected from our
instagram and facebook photos and we're
gonna do a shout out to russell russell
awesome job on your bathroom renovation
now listen guys if you want to get a
shout out let us know give us your name
give us your city where you're from and
then share your project it's absolutely
amazing to see you guys working hard diy
in your houses but you gotta follow us
on our socials instagram and facebook
check the information note below in the
video description jump in there and
start sending us your pictures of your
success stories okay we'd like to share
with the world so everybody else can be
encouraged to go ahead and diy too
cheers well done let's get back to the
video here we go now now we got the
paint brush working i'm going to show
you how to cut the outside of a wall
generally speaking outside corners are
sharp edges you want to use the heel of
the brush which is this part right here
set your brush on it and it'll fan out
again draw about a quarter inch away and
you get a ridge paint now you come back
with the paint
and you can
just draw right up against the edge of
that that corner
you don't ever want to use a roller here
when you stand on the other side looking
this way you don't want to see two
colors
all right this is the secret
so if you just use the heel
draw a line and then you can push that
paint right up to the edge
you'll get a perfect edge that's how the
pro is cut in the corners
now if you're going to be painting your
walls and you're changing the color
you're not going to want to change all
your baseboards and paint them again and
all your other trim again it's just like
the ceiling only upside down the secret
here
you want your head to be able to see
underneath
so you got to get close to the ground
here
same thing draw that line but a quarter
inch out make sure you don't have too
much paint in your brush for this
and you can push it down
and then you can just pull it forward
if you're collecting too much paint pull
it away and start over
there we go
that's a nice edge
this is one of the highest quality
paints on the market today this is the
new poly
poly way
this looks like a one coat coverage
paint but it's not
we've shown you how to cut the ceiling
how to do outside corners how to cut the
trim i'm going to just cut the rest of
this room real quick because you want to
do all of your brush work and then roll
your first coat the only other thing you
need to know about cutting in is this
when you've got wall plugs and switches
outlets
okay you want to brush the region
because you never want your roller to
get too close
sure sign of someone being in too much
of a hurry is when the electrical socket
has got paint all over it
okay and if you find yourself just a
little bit too much paint you can see
the brush marks
dust it out
get rid of those
there we go now it's time to roll so
we're all done the cut in now it's time
to do the rolling but before you do that
remember we're dealing with uh paint's
got a lot of technology and acrylic in
it time to wash this brush okay don't
wait to the end of the job or the brush
should be garbage that is a pro tip
all right well here's the rig
this has got the rest of our paint in it
okay
all right what i want to do is i want to
first i want to load the roller up this
takes a minute
okay it's just a matter of pushing that
paint in there
and get it nice and full
there we go
be patient
now if you have good quality paint it
won't drip
you get what you paint for right there
guys
now
for the rolling hallways are amazingly
difficult because
working with a stick oh look at that it
just passes it just clears
so if i don't extend it i can work all
the way top to bottom and that's how you
want to roll
none of this w business you want to just
get this up here
and just really lightly hardly touch the
wall
okay and the paint will come off all on
its own all right and then you want to
go about
two rollers wide
and then you want to go back where you
started
because there's a lot of extra paint on
that part of the wall
you want to get close to the edge but
not over the edge so about a half an
inch away
and that'll add texture to that earlier
brushwork
i always stop a few inches from the
bottom and a few inches from the top
that's why my cut line is about four
inches tall
so i never risk hitting the ceiling
all right
what we're doing here right now we're
trying to make the texture on the wall
consistent
every every paint company's got a
different coverage the materials are
made differently
okay and if you find that your wall just
looks too wet and too thick
keep stretching this out until it's not
the case anymore
i'm being blown away with the coverage
of this paint i love this new cabinet
trim and wall paint man
that's awesome okay and if you have
saggy texture
or it's a little different just back
roll
now that the roller is getting dry it'll
pick up the extra paint off the wall
and it'll make sure everything looks the
same okay this is not about speed this
is about perfection
let's not be like these guys that are
out there with a double wide roller
trying to paint a whole wall in nine
seconds
that's a disaster it always is
because this paint has great coverage
we're going to leave a bit of a gap this
time so when we back roll we can roll
back onto it
now there's a lot in painting it's
called the wet edge
now i did not pick up as much paint as
the first time here
because
i'm just trying to make this easy the
wet edge
is right here
okay
and you always want to be painting where
the wet edge is before it starts to dry
remember we talked about paints nowadays
having a lot of technology in them
and it might say on the can it takes two
hours to dry
but that's just because there are still
houses out there that are left in
plaster
and if you see any lint get rid of it
and back roll it
there are still houses out there that
are laughing plaster and that technology
does take about two hours for an acrylic
paint to dry so the instructions on the
can are based on worst conditions truth
is this stuff can dry in 20 minutes on
the wall so you want to keep your lead
edge wet
which means if you start painting with
the roller and the phone rings you don't
stop painting you finish the wall and
you call them back or you will have a
definitive ridge
it'll dry in that few minutes that
you're gone
and then you're gonna have to pull out
the sanding block you're really just
melting this paint
into itself
to get a perfect look now if you've
never seen anybody paint with a stick
like this before how easy does that look
compared to hold on to it by hand
this stick only costs about 20
and you're gonna reach you don't need a
ladder
gravity does have to work
there we go
nice and controlled straight up and down
and then back roll to pick up the extra
paint
leave the texture consistent on the wall
and that is all you need to know
the truth is if you use good quality
tools and good quality paint painting is
easy
yep
it's actually a lot of fun
anyone who says they don't like to paint
is doing it wrong
this is incredibly satisfying
i have one more rule
because when you're rolling with a paint
you're actually rolling in a direction
and you create a grain with the texture
and you may not see it as long as you're
always rolling in the same direction
resist the temptation to ever change the
direction of the roll
okay
if you have a big window here and you
only have a one foot section of wall
don't go left to right
it'll show you'll actually see it in the
texture in the wall that you change
directions
just use your roller down here like this
and do short little rolls
never change the direction of the roller
on a wall
ever
best thing about modern paint guys is
about an hour after you've done the
first coat you can jump into the second
coat if you've got conditioned air if
you've got air conditioning or a decent
heating system in your home not going to
be a problem just throw a fan on for a
few minutes and help speed up the drying
process and then you're going to want to
sand one more time do this
check your walls you'll feel it okay
one more time
because this paint is only an hour old
you will actually see
all the changes of where you actually
sanded something off as well if you look
down the light properly
okay look we we just tried to bring the
camera over so you can because i can see
this playing his day up against the
light the camera can't pick it up uh
truth is cameras lie
everything you're looking at on youtube
looks ten times better than it does in
reality the secret is when you're doing
your paint job
just trust me and do the sand in between
coats feel the wall before you sand and
after it'll blow your mind the
difference in the texture okay
this is the secret it's all right to
having a great finish i'm going to show
you how to do the second cut because the
second cut is where you get your
precision line
whenever you're painting a flat surface
you need to do the precision cut on the
second coat what it is is there's just
there's not as much resistance so you
don't need a lot of paint in your brush
and able to draw a perfect line without
having it snow plow up on you you know
what i mean right so here let's just
show you so here's the thing you push
the brush in you load it up
and then you clean it off
okay you don't want too much paint you
want it inside the brush not on top of
it
now
we're going to be running
a nice long straight line again right
underneath the other one
but this time we're going to push the
brush right into the crack right into
the crease
you can come at it from either side
all right
and you're just going to use the tip of
that brush
okay and that's how you get a nice
straight line
if you use too much paint or you push
too hard or you try to be too quick
you're going to push it all over the
ceiling
but just a little bit of
pressure and because you're painting
from inside the brush you can actually
put the bristles right into the corner
and it'll come out perfect i got to get
that corner here we go kind of leaning
off the ladder here a little too much
now one of the rules when you're doing
your second coat
every wall surface that you paint you
paint all the cut on one wall and then
you roll that wall and then you move to
the next one because the first coat it's
okay if you can see the lines in the
roller it doesn't really matter the
first cut takes a long time
but once you get that first coat dry you
want to make sure you're finishing one
surface at a time
okay so you cut and roll each surface
individually
and that is how you're going to make
sure that you can blend
we talked about the wet edge this cut
can be wet the same time as i'm rolling
so now i'm blending the brush marks in
with the roller to put texture on it and
then you won't see brush marks
now if you're interested in learning
about how to do diy renovations
we have lots of videos on the channel to
help you with projects
the thing is
there's a lot of changes that have
happened in the industry
with building technology and
construction technology over the last
i'm going to say 80 years
ever since 1941 when they started the
national building code
a lot of different materials have come
out and different technologies so we
went from laughing plaster to drywall
with plaster from oil based to acrylic
paints uh
so
there's no such thing as a need for
primer if you're anything after 1975
unless they had oil paint on there for
some reason
you only need to use a transition primer
in certain circumstances the truth is
not everything is as simple as you like
it to be so considered joining a
membership program for five dollars a
month
you can have access to our forum and an
email or you can send in pictures and
ask us questions about your particular
job all you got to do is tell us the age
of your home and where you live and then
put in the question we'll be able to
help you up so when you're doing your
second roll you want to start where you
started your cut in so that you're
trying to get
the wet roller making contact with the
wet brushwork
okay
that's about it
resist the temptation to use too much
product you can tell when you're using
quality paint you get great hide already
so we're just looking for an extra 30
hide so you can stretch it out instead
of one roller you can go two or three
the only other thing you want to do is
try not to roll dry
don't roll it so it gets so dry that
you're pushing too hard it just makes it
a lot of work
all right
you should be able to just
move the stick up and down without
putting a lot of pressure
and get the job accomplished
remember this is supposed to be fun not
a lot of work okay
all right
so you can see that after two coats with
the bright kind of finish and good
distribution of the paint you get a
really good look now
one more thing you need to know is that
most paints on the market that have a
high wash ability high durability
technology are also a 30-day curing
process okay
that means that after you've done the
painting it might be dry within a couple
hours it might feel nice and hard the
next day but resist the temptation to
hang pictures or mount fixtures or
anything like that on a freshly painted
surface for at least 48 hours give it
two days make sure it really starts to
get hard
and after 30 days you can then be free
to do any kind of washing
if you get some dirty fingerprints or
some crayon on the paint don't wash it
off for the first 30 days because you're
going to interrupt with the curing
process and you'll get that smudge mark
it'll wreck your paint job all right
all right if that information is helpful
to you then give this video a thumbs up
all right welcome to youtube we need the
engagement guys so don't forget to
subscribe to the channel hit that little
bell icon for notifications which is
youtube's way of telling you the next
time a video comes up and remember guys
if you're doing renovations or
remodeling and building projects at home
and you need help consider joining our
membership program we understand that
there's a lot of information a lot of
learning and a lot of different homes
and different geographies
everybody has specific needs the
membership program is designed so that
you can have access to me and i can help
answer your questions you can even send
us pictures in our members forum that
we've created for you okay it's only
five dollars a month and you get great
access to us and the live shows as well
so come along for the ride and if you're
working on an older house that needs a
lot of patching repairs then consider
clicking this video right here we did
this a few years ago it teaches all my
tips and tricks so that you can make
your house look brand new before you
paint because that's the secret to
success cheers till next time