if you've got a piece of furniture at
home that you would like to update with
a little bit of paint
but you've got no idea where to start
then this video's for you
i'm going to take you through my
furniture painting process
telling you what steps to take and why
with no fancy tools
[Music]
if you're new here welcome my name is
katie i am the k
and salvaged by k scott i'm a full-time
furniture painter and i've been running
my
very own very successful furniture
flipping business
right here out of my home for the past
five years for a
ton more furniture flipping tips tricks
and inspiration make sure that you tap
that subscribe button and have the bell
notification turn on
so that you never miss out on a brand
new flip this little accent table
is the piece i'm going to be working on
with you guys today and my biggest piece
of advice to
anyone that is brand new to furniture
painting
is to start small and just keep it
simple i like to start off every
furniture flip with a really good
cleaning
today i'm just using some dawn dish soap
but really
any type of cleaner that you have or
that you like
that has a good degreasing factor in it
is going to do you the best service here
we want to remove any obvious cobwebs
or dust that is on the piece but we also
want to clean away
any grease from furniture polishes over
the years
or fingerprints around knobs that stuff
is really going to repel
a new painted finish so it's gotta go
once your piece is nice and clean
it is important to go back with some
clean clear water and rinse away any
soap residue
once i was finished cleaning i let my
table dry really well for a few hours
and then i moved it out onto the back
deck because
it's a really nice day and my next step
is sanding which is going to make a
little bit of a mess
i'm starting off with a foam sanding pad
this is an old one that doesn't have any
real grit left on it
so i just wrapped a piece of 80 grit
coarse
sandpaper around it and i'm going to use
this to remove
any of this old flaking finish
off of my table each piece is going to
be a little bit different
if the piece that you're working on has
a finish on it that is still
intact and not loose or flaking up
you don't need to do this really coarse
80 grit sand
you can get away just with a light scuff
sand
in my case this needs to be removed
because if i go ahead and apply my new
finish
on top of this failing finish my new
finish is going to fail as well
the base of this table is in much better
condition
finish wise it is not flaking or peeling
off at all
so i switched out my sandpaper to a
much softer 220 grit and i'm just
lightly scuffing up the surface i don't
need to remove the previous finish
i just want to scratch it up a little
bit and give my paint
something good to hold onto
[Music]
i did also go back over that top surface
with the softer 220 grit sandpaper just
to smooth out any harsh
scratch marks that may be left behind by
that 80 grit that i started with
[Music]
once i was all done with my sanding i
came back with just a clean
damp rag and wiped away any dust that
was left behind
the next step in my painting process is
always
primer i'm going to be using my all-time
favorite
zinzer bin shellac base primer this
primer serves
a couple of different important purposes
one
the shellac in it is going to block in
any wood
tannins or the naturally occurring oils
in
the wood and the wood stain on this
piece
those oils tend to bleed up
through water-based paint finishes or
top coats and leave
really ugly stain marks in your new
finish
the bin shellac based primer will
prevent that from happening
it's also going to give me a nice smooth
unified surface between the bare wood
top that i now have and the existing
finish
on the base that's going to make sure
that my paint is
sitting the same and absorbing the same
amount
into those two different substrates if i
didn't have this primer on the top and
the bottom
the paint would absorb differently into
that bare wood top
as opposed to sitting on top of the
previous finish
and you'd be able to see the difference
this primer
is messy and stinky so i like to line my
paint tray with a little bit of tin foil
you also need to make sure that you mix
this product very well the shellac tends
to separate out of it if it's sitting in
the can for a while
and i wear gloves and use it outside or
in a
very well ventilated area it does have a
strong odor
my favorite way to apply this is with a
four inch
microfiber roller you can by all means
use a foam roller or a cheap disposable
brush
i wouldn't use a good high quality brush
with this stuff because it's
really hard to clean up so i like to use
something that i can
use once and toss when i'm done using my
roller i'm going to apply
a coat evenly over the entire table
this is a very thin runny product so you
do want to watch for
[Music]
drips
i usually apply two coats of this primer
to
my pieces that's usually enough to block
in any
wood tannin bleed through situations
and make sure that everything is nice
and smooth it dries really fast you only
need maybe
15 or 20 minutes between coats just make
sure that you wrap up your
roller and any primer that is left in
your paint tray
in a plastic grocery bag so it doesn't
dry out
my primer is dry so i moved my table
back inside and i'm just going to give
it a really
light smoothing sand with some
very fine sandpaper this is a 400 grit
just to smooth out any of that bumpy
roller texture that can happen sometimes
now that we've got all of that prep work
out of the way
it is time to add some color to this
piece
i chose to use melange paint on this
project which is
an artisan style mineral paint and i'm
going to be using the color
sonora rose melange is a brand new
small veteran-owned business out of
sugarland texas
they have created this beautiful
luxurious
buttery paint specifically made for
furniture applications
like this their hand poured paint
comes in four different size
eco-friendly
glass jars and their palette is
incredible
they have so many colors and are adding
new ones
all the time i'm applying my paint today
with a
zebra fan brush this is a really
great inexpensive all-purpose
brush for furniture i like to apply
my paint in light thin coats
as opposed to trying to get full
coverage in the first
go this is really going to help prevent
brush strokes or building up any texture
if you're going for a really smooth
sleek finish
i am personally a very messy brusher
my technique is always just to get the
paint
on there and then i come back with a
very
light hand and smooth out all of the
brush strokes in the same direction
this paint has incredible coverage on
the first
coat but depending on the paint that
you're using
you may notice that it's very splotchy
or patchy looking and that is completely
normal remember light thin
coats you want to build your coverage
gradually
so that you're avoiding creating any
texture or brush strokes
apache finish will fill itself in with
the second or third coat of paint
[Music]
once i was finished with my first coat i
closed up my jar of paint and tucked my
brush
into a little plastic baggie to keep it
fresh
while i'm waiting for this to dry
[Music]
my first coat is dry and you can
definitely see
it is streaky and patchy totally normal
like i said
don't freak out this is all gonna fill
in with your second coat
and if it doesn't fill in with your
second coat it's no big deal to go back
for a third
like i said melange is a brand new small
family-owned business and morgan the
creator of this paint line
has been working really hard to find an
efficient
and economical way to start shipping up
to canada
which all of us canadians know can be
ridiculously expensive
and she just may have a canadian
retailer in line
any day now wink wink nudge nudge
as soon as there is a canadian retailer
set up and ready i will pin that link in
the comments section of this video
or if you want to shop now whether
you're in canada or the us
you can use code salvaged 10 to save 10
on your order at melangepaints.com the
current cost to ship to canada
is somewhere between twenty and thirty
dollars depending on what you order
us orders have a ten dollar flat fee
or free shipping on orders over seventy
five dollars
once you're finished painting if you
notice that you have
a slight amount of brush strokes or
texture that you're not happy with
you can always go back over your paint
again with a super
soft fine grit sandpaper like a 320
or 400 grit just to smooth things out
then we are ready to seal everything up
and give it
a few good coats of protection
[Music]
i'm going to be using my all-time
favorite verithane
diamond wood finish in a satin sheen
this is a very
user friendly water-based poly top coat
i like to pour a little bit out into a
separate container
and mix in a tiny bit of my paint to
tint my top coat
most furniture paints on the markets are
matte and porous that really helps them
stick to
furniture pieces but it also means that
they do need
some additional top coat protection
that's going to seal in that matte
porous paint
make it wipeable and protect it from
finger marks and just general wear and
tear
when you're brushing on a liquid top
coat like this
you're going to want to work in small
sections again
i like to get it on really quickly and
then come back
and smooth it over with a very light
hand
all in one direction after that don't
touch it if you notice that you've got a
bare patch
or you're not liking the look of it
just leave it alone let it dry don't
fuss with
it if there's something wrong we'll fix
it later
[Music]
this specific top coat needs one to two
hours
to dry between coats i left this for
about an hour and a half and then i came
back again
with my super fine grit sandpaper just
to smooth it out
this is the time if you have a drip or
an area that you're
not really in love with you can use this
super fine sandpaper
to buff that out a little bit again you
want to do that when the top coat is dry
not when it's wet or you'll just make a
mess just like with the paint
the second coat is really going to make
the difference here
and we're going to use this to fill in
any patchy areas
areas that we missed areas that we
weren't really in love with
on the first pass and give everything a
really
beautiful unified satin sheen
one more quick nugget of advice here
is something that seems so simple but it
is really easy to overlook
there are so many different paints and
paint products out on the market right
now and they all vary
slightly it's really important to take
the time
to research the products that you're
using
and just read the label they're going to
tell you
everything that you need to know to
apply to your specific project
from application to drying times
curing times recommended temperatures
all of that stuff is right on the label
once my second coat of top coat was dry
i was really happy with the finish that
i had
so i tucked the drawer back in attached
a new knob
and this is what our finished piece
looks like
[Music]
i know that getting started on your very
first furniture painting project
can be really intimidating but i hope
that this video gave you
lots of guidance and is gonna get you
started in a not so scary way
again please make sure that you are
subscribed to the channel before you go
i'm gonna leave a few more videos here
that i think you might like
and i will catch you guys next time
[Music]