what's up everybody's Charles today I'm
going to show you how to lift your
vehicle all four wheels off the ground
on four jack stands now we're gonna be
using my mark seven and a half of golf R
for this job
so if you drive that kind of car you hit
the jackpot otherwise what we're gonna
talk about today does apply to basically
any vehicle typically I like to only
lift either the front or the rear up at
one time but there's a handful of jobs
that require all four wheels off the
ground or for the car to be level things
like manual transmission service Haldex
service we need the car level or if
we're doing things like rotating the
tires or bleeding brakes it's nice to
have all four wheels off the ground
because safety is our number one concern
here we want to make sure we do some
things before actually lifting the car
one we want to make sure we're on a
level hard surface if you're working on
hot asphalt you may want to take a piece
of metal or a piece of wood underneath
your jack and your jack stands so the
car doesn't sink into the asphalt and if
we can avoid it we definitely don't want
to do this on grass sand or gravel next
we want to make sure that the steering
wheel is straight we want to make sure
the car is in park or if it's a manual
transmission in first gear we want to go
ahead and set the parking brake and
we're going to be chalking the front and
the rear wheels once we've secured the
vehicle go ahead and do a quick check of
your jack stands and make sure that
they're in good condition and I always
like to test the floor jack and have a
little fun while doing it also every car
is different so you want to refer to
your vehicle owners manual to see the
proper lifting points on your car some
vehicles have the lifting point in the
very front or the very rear of the
vehicle which makes lifting that end of
the car much much easier because this VW
has so much plastic we don't want to
lift it up by the front core support or
the rear bumper that can cause damage to
the vehicle so I'm gonna show you how I
do it
again keeping safety in mind also after
you lift the vehicle if you're gonna be
taking the wheels off it's a good idea
to go ahead and loosen those lug bolts
and lug nuts a little bit before lifting
the car once we have our vehicle in the
proper spot where we're going to lift it
next we need to find the pinch welds
under our car now if your vehicle has a
full frame this makes it really easy
just use the frame typically a unibody
car like this is going to have four
points on the vehicle that are actually
meant for lifting these are reinforced
areas on the pinch weld right behind the
front tires and right in front of the
rear tires
these spots typically hang down a little
bit lower than the rest of the pinch
weld or can even be
indicated by a notch or something on the
body of the car now if your car has a
side skirt or something low like this
you may want to take a hockey puck or a
block of wood to extend the distance
between the side skirt and the jack we
don't want to crush our side skirt when
we lift up our car once we have
everything in place and we found the
pinch weld we want to set the jack as
perpendicular to the body line of the
car as we can now you really want to
take your time here to make sure the
jack pad or the hockey puck whatever
you're using is is centered on the pinch
weld as you can get it I like to slowly
put the jack up to the vehicle then go
ahead and give it a pump and make sure
that it's secured we also want to look
and make sure we're not doing any damage
to the pinch weld here if you feel like
it's bending lower the jack down and
reset it now from here we can go ahead
and lift our car up we noticed something
really awesome about a car like this it
lifts the front and the back up so we're
gonna start with the jack stand at the
back of the vehicle now there's two main
kinds of jack stands we have the ones
with the flat pad and ones with the
grooved pad both work really well so use
what you have one thing I don't like to
do is take the jack stand and extend it
all the way out it makes me a little
uncomfortable when it's at its top
setting so we're gonna actually drop it
down one lower than that I also like to
take a little piece of shop rag to
protect the pinch weld and set it on top
we're gonna leave this one here we're
gonna set the front now when it comes to
setting the front I like to put the jack
stand on the subframe if possible this
can get a little tricky if you're doing
something like working on the subframe
once we get the car off the ground I'll
show you how to move the jack stands so
that it's not up on the subframe in case
you're doing work there so we're gonna
take our jack stand I like to go just
behind the control arm there's a really
nice spot right here so we're going just
behind this front bolt for the lower
control arm there are multiple places
you could put the jack stand underneath
on the subframe you just want to make
sure that it's as close to the outside
of the vehicle as possible because we
are gonna put one on the other side once
we have our jack stands properly secured
we're going to very slowly lower the car
down keep in mind that the car may
actually shift a little bit while you're
lowering it down so go as slow as you
possibly can
once the weight of the vehicle is on the
jack stands you can go ahead and lower
the jack all the way and then just
double check and make sure your jack
stands are properly centered now you may
feel the car's not up high enough we can
raise it up a little bit at a time once
we get the whole car off the ground now
we're gonna do the same thing on the
other side all right we'll start with
the back again get our jack stand in
place something we want to pay attention
to on this side though we want to make
sure that we have the jack stand set at
the same height that we had the other
side the same height we had the other
side left three holes exposed so we're
gonna set it there just like that we'll
get our needlessly OCD shop rag set on
there and we'll go ahead and center it
right in the pinch weld now we'll do the
front next want to do the same thing in
the front as we did in the back two
holes exposed just like the other side
and we want to set it right in the same
place and again very slowly and
carefully lower the jack down once you
have the entire vehicle up on the jack
stands give the car a little shake and
make sure it's properly secured couple
other things I like to do I like to
leave the jack underneath the car with
just a touch of pressure holding the car
up this is just one backup in case
something crazy happens also if you're
taking the wheels off go ahead and slide
the wheel and tire assembly underneath
the car so that if it does slip it'll
land on the wheel and tire assembly not
on your face now if you need to do work
on the subframe we can't support the car
with the subframe so what we're gonna do
once the cars off the ground and
properly secured we're gonna take our
floor jack we're gonna slide it up
underneath the car to the subframe now I
like to lift it right in front of where
the center dog-bone mount is or the
pendulum mount not on the bushing but
right in front of it if you go up in
that bushing hole you're just gonna
probably knock the bushing out lift the
car up once the car is lifted off the
jack stands we can go ahead and move
those two jack stands to the front pinch
welds and now one thing I do want to do
is I want to raise this up
so it has three holes exposed to match
how high I have the back ones that way
when we set the car down it'll be nice
and level alright so there we have it
our cars properly lifted secured ready
to go for whatever job we're going to do
for me I think it's time to put some
wheel spacers and new wheel bolts on
give this car a little bit better
fitment for the wheel and tire guys
there's always questions or comments
drop them down below if you liked the
video hit that thumbs up button don't
forget to subscribe thank you guys so
much for watching and I'll talk to you
again next time